<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and notable sermon vpon the text Vos autem non sic. But you not so Lately preached vpon speciall occasion, by M. Butler of Owndell, in S. Maries Church in the Vniuersity of Cambridge: and succinctly debating the chiefe matters, which are now in question in the Church of England. Verie profitable for the further resoluing of them, who being brought into suspence by the contradiction of ministers, are content to lend an indifferent eare vnto the truth.</title>
            <author>Butler, of Oundle.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 951:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and notable sermon vpon the text Vos autem non sic. But you not so Lately preached vpon speciall occasion, by M. Butler of Owndell, in S. Maries Church in the Vniuersity of Cambridge: and succinctly debating the chiefe matters, which are now in question in the Church of England. Verie profitable for the further resoluing of them, who being brought into suspence by the contradiction of ministers, are content to lend an indifferent eare vnto the truth.</title>
                  <author>Butler, of Oundle.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [R. Field for] Iohn VVolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Possibly one of the Richard Butlers at Cambridge."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Vos autem non sic.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Lambeth Palace.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21700:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21700:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEARNED AND NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE SERMON VPON THE TEXT VOS AVTEM NON SIC. <hi>But you not ſo.</hi> Lately preached vpon ſpeciall occaſion, by M. <hi>Butler</hi> of Owndell, in S. Maries Church in the Vniuerſity of Cambridge: and ſuccinctly debating the chiefe matters, which are now in queſtion in the Church of England. <hi>Verie profitable for the further reſoluing of them, who being brought into ſuſpence by the contradiction of Miniſters, are content to lend an indifferent eare vnto the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Wolfe, featuring a framed fleur-de-lis seeding, with two cherubs (McKerrow 294)</figDesc>
               <head>I W</head>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON. Printed by Iohn VVolfe. 1593.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21700:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21700:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He neceſsitie of theſe our times requiring the helpe of all hands, to the quenching of that fire, vvhich hath of late bene kindled in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish church, by certaine factious and ſedicious firebrandes: I could not (gentle Reader) but impart vnto thee, the frutefull labors of the Author hereof, a diligent labourer and aſsiſtant in that buſineſſe, and that not vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſcorching of thoſe flames vvhich he ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish. And though that dangerous fire (God be praiſed) be novv ſo vvell allayed, through the prouident circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſome vvorthie perſonages, and no leſſe vvorthy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of diuerſe learned men, vvho lately haue layed their hands vnto this vvorke, that all danger of further procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is cleane taken avvay: yet this helpe alſo, shall come (I hope) not out of ſeaſon, if but to the quenching of that ſmoke vvherevvith that ſmothered fire ſtill offendeth the eyes of the better ſort. The copie of this Sermon comming to my handes, not by the Author ſelfe vvho firſt made it, and then vvrit it: but by an auditor that heard it vvhen it vvas preached, I thought good to permit it to the cenſure of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate friend, before I vvould commit it to the preſſe. VVho vpon the firſt ſight of it, euen before he had peruſed it, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo bene a hearer) gaue this good teſtimonie of it, that it neede not feare the cenſure of any priuate man, vvhich had paſsed alreadie the cenſure of a vvhole Vniuerſitie, and
<pb facs="tcp:21700:3"/> that vvith the general approbation of the common ſuffrage: excepting onely a fevv odde and ſingular fellovves, vvho being foreſtalled vvith a left hand perſvvaſion of the cauſe it ſelfe, cannot brooke the impeachment of their ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion: and therefore vſe of cuſtome to runne against the common ſtreame of all other men. This then, vvas his firſt opinion of it. But hauing peruſed it, he further added, that of manie bookes vvhich of late haue bene published in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, not manie haue contriued in ſo short a a compaſſe, ſo manie great matters of queſtion and controuerſie: it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the grounds of all the chiefe queſtions, vvhich at this day do exerciſe the Church of England. All vvhich he hath not only vvith ſingular dexteritie and art, and yet very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, raiſed out of his short Text, but alſo layed open and dilated ſo fully as the quickneſſe of ſo learned an auditory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and a great deale more fully, than in that shortneſſe of time could be expected. This iudgement being deliuered to me of this Sermon, I could not vvith equitie but ſend it vnto thee, vvith the ſame commendation, vvith vvhich it came commended vnto me, both by the firſt and ſecond cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of a learned man, I being content to haue vſed another mans better eyes, vvhere the vveake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine ovvne, vvould not ſuffer my ſelfe ſo vvell to iudge.</p>
            <trailer>Fare-vvell.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21700:3"/>
            <head>A LEARNED SERMON PREACHED NOT LONG SINCE IN S. MARIES CHVRCH IN THE Vniuerſitie of Cambridge: ſuccinctly debating the chiefe of thoſe matters, which are now in queſtion in the Church of England.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke 22. ver. 26.</bibl> But you not ſo: But let him that is or shall be greater amongeſt you, be as the younger, and the ruler as he that ministreth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, deuide them ſelues into two parts. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>dehortation:</hi> in theſe words: <hi>But you not ſo:</hi> in which our Sauiour dehorteth his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, from ambition and tyrannie.</p>
            <p>An <hi>exhortation:</hi> in the other wordes: <hi>but let him that is, or shall be greater amongſt you, be as the yonger: and the ruler, as he that miniſtreth.</hi> That is, that in their ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and authoritie, they ſhould be humble: and behaue themſelues as <hi>Miniſters,</hi> miniſtring good to all.</p>
            <p>Of the later of theſe two parts, containing very good, and fit matter for this place (becauſe of the time) I ſhall not be able to intreate. I will therefore keepe my ſelfe within the compaſſe of the firſt, namely the <hi>dehortation: But you not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21700:4"/>
            <p>Which words do ſeeme to be ſomewhat imperfect, and therfore leſt I ſhould be thought to ad anie thing of mine owne, I will borrow the words of the Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Mathevv</hi> chap. 20. 26. &amp; Saint <hi>Marke</hi> chap. 10. 43. who writ one and the ſelfe ſame thing: ſo to make the ſence it ſhalbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In theſe words there are three, which containe ſome difficultie in them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>it shall not be.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>ſo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>you or vvith you.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>So that, for the vnderſtanding of the meaning of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, we muſt ſearch out, what is meant by, <hi>It shall not be;</hi> what by, <hi>ſo:</hi> what by, <hi>you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It shall not be.</hi> This kinde of phraſe of ſpeech, in our Engliſh tongue, is vſed two maner of wayes, either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding a thing to be done, or foretelling a thing not to be done: As when a maiſter ſaith to his ſeruant, This ſhall not be done to day, or, It ſhall not be done to day. In this ſpeech, he doth forbid a thing to be done. But when an Aſtronomer ſhall ſay, of the weather, It ſhall not be hot, drie, cold, or rainie, on ſuch a day, or ſuch a moneth, In this kinde of ſpeech he doth not forbid, but foreſhewe a thing that ſhal not be. In theſe two ſences, are theſe words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>it shall not be,</hi> vſed in the Scriptures: namely either forbidding a thing to be done, in which ſence, <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiuely:</hi> or foretelling a thing not to be done, in which <hi>Prophetically. Prophetically,</hi> theſe words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are vſed Apoc. 10. 6. where the Angell ſweareth: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>that it shall not be time any more:</hi> prophecying, and foretelling a thing that ſhall not be. So likewiſe it is taken Apoc. 22. 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>and it shall not be night there,</hi> prophecying of the eſtate of the kingdome of heauen.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21700:4"/> This I take it, is the reaſon, why ſome haue thought Chriſt to ſpeake prophetically in this place.</p>
            <p>If it be taken prophetically, then it muſt needes be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a prophecie of the eſtate of his Diſciples, in this life, or in the life to come. If in this life, then the ſence is this: <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles do rule, and thoſe that are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, are called good doers: But you not ſo.</hi> That is, I do foreſhew vnto you, that you ſhal not be ſo. As if he ſhould ſay: they, in their authoritie, are called good doers: but you, exerciſing authoritie, ſhalbe called bad doers: they ruling euilly, are called good men: you ruling well, ſhall be called euill men. In which ſence, our Sauiour Chriſt is made to ſpeake in this place, all one with that, which in another place, elſewhere he ſaith: <hi>The Diſciple is not greater than his Maiſter: If they haue called me Beelzebub, they shall alſo call you. Me,</hi> that came to miniſter good to them, and to giue my life for them: euen ſo you, that in your authority, ſhall procure the welfare of all, and ſpend your liues to do good to all. This ſence is true, for by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable experience, we find it to be ſo, when as amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, ſome, for their ſuperioritie are called Antichriſtes: ſome for their authoritie, Tyrants: for dealing iuſtly, without partialitie, cruell men: for reſtraining the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of certaine perſons, Perſecutors. This ſence though good, yet doth it not fit this place, my reaſon is this. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Sauiour Chriſt preſently after ſaith <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let him be,</hi> ſpeaking Imperatiuely.</p>
            <p>If we take it to be a prophecie of the life to come, then the ſence is, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles do rule ouer them: But you not ſo.</hi> That is, in my kingdome (which you falſly imagine to be vpon earth) I do foreſhew vnto you, that it ſhal not be ſo. In which ſence, our ſauiour Chriſt is made
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21700:5"/> to rebuke two things in his Diſciples. Firſt, that they am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly ſought to be each of them ouer other. Secondly, that they preferred earth before heauen, and the hauing of a kingdome vpon earth, before the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>This ſence is the better thought of: Firſt, becauſe in this place our Sauiour Chriſt doth rebuke the ambitious ſtrife for rule that was in his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it was the manner of our Sauiour Chriſt, to drawe them from the cogitation of earthly things, as Luke 12. 32. from too much caring for foode, and apparell, to the earneſt deſire of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in theſe words, <hi>Feare not litle flocke, it is your fathers vvill to giue you a kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe immediatly after, verſe 29. our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſpeaketh of his kingdome. <hi>And I appoint vnto you, as my Father hath appointed vnto me, a kingdome: that you may eate and drinke, at my table in my kingdome, iudging the tvvelue Tribes of Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſence is good, for by lamentable experience, we find it to be true, when as ſome ſo vnſatiably hunt after honor, that if they may but ſit in the ſeat of honor, though they die ſo ſoone as they be ſet, they care not. Theſe, do ſo much account of earth, that they care not for heauen: as appeareth by ſo great coſt, beſtowed vpon great ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous houſes and ſtately pallaces, and litle or no proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſent vp to heauen: by which they ſhew plainly, that they neuer mind to dwell there, and onely to dwell on earth: whereas, alas poore ſoules, they are but tenaunts at will, without any ſtate of inheritaunce, or tearme of yeares, and caſt out to day or to morrow, at the will of the Lord. This ſence therefore, though good, and fitting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21700:5"/> other places of the Scripture, yet doth it not fit this place. my reaſons are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt our Sauiour Chriſt, Matt. 20. 28. propoundeth his maner of liuing here being conuerſant vpon earth, as a patterne vnto his Diſciples: which can not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the life to come, but of this life, ſaying vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>As the Sonne of man came not to be miniſtred vnto, but to miniſter, and to giue his life for manie:</hi> inſinuating, that they in like maner, in their ſuperioritie, and authoritie ouer others, here vpon earth, ſhould not propound this to them ſelues, to be miniſtred vnto: that is, to haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at their commaund, as ſlaues to do their will, but to miniſter, that is, to employ them ſelues to the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for the procuring thereof, to ſpend their liues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe the Euangeliſts, Saint Mathew and Saint Marke haue theſe wordes, <hi>He that vvill be greater:</hi> which words import two things: firſt a change of eſtate, from lower to higher, and from leſſer to greater. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a deſire to be in other eſtate: which two things cannot fit the kingdome of heauen, for there all things are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and therefore not ſubiect to change. And our eſtate there, ſhall be an happie eſtate, and we ſhall deſire no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe the Euangeliſts compared together, do declare, that by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our Sauiour meaneth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let it not be.</hi> For whereas the Euangeliſt Saint Marke, Chap. 10. 43. hath <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: verſe 44. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Saint Matthewe 20. 26. hath, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: verſe 27. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is therefore in this place ſpoken Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiuely, forbidding a thing to be done, that is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, to tyrannize, which is, either ouer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21700:6"/> the goods, bodies, or ſoules of men. Ouer the goods of men, by taking away by force violently, or by deceipt guilefully, the leaſes, lands, goods, or poſſeſſions of men. Ouer the bodies of men: by hurting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by falſe impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, by murthering them, by countenancing mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, or acquitting murtherers. Ouer the ſoules of men: by cauſing them to ſweare, and forſweare them ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, to vſe will as a lawe, which is, when the wil of ſome great man, ſhall be a ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſtay, or peruert iuſtice, or when any in authoritie ſhall be led by his owne will, of affection, or malice, to peruert iuſtice. On the contrarie ſide, he doth command, or at the leaſt commend, to rule iuſtly: for no forbidding precept, but doth either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, or commend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, that is, doth either like, or not diſlike the contrarie. And thus much for the words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt doth not forbid authoritie to his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſo.</hi> This word is taken diuerſly of ſundrie men. I do not purpoſe to name the perſons, but reciting all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, which with anie ſhew of reaſon haue, or can be gathered, I purpoſe to ſet downe ſo neare as I can, the purpoſe and intent of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Some attribute <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: making the ſence thus, <hi>They that are in authoritie, are called</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which word is of ſome tranſlated <hi>gratious Lords: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not be called Lords.</p>
            <p>Others attribute <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, making the ſence thus, <hi>The kings of the Gentiles do rule: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not rule.</p>
            <p>Others, though they attribute it to the ſame verbe, yet make the ſence thus. <hi>The kings of the Gentiles do rule: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not rule.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21700:6"/>
            <p>So either titles of honour, as Lord, ruler, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ruling, or ſo ruling, is forbidden.</p>
            <p>Titles of honor, whether Lord, ruler, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are not forbidden.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath not one ſillable in it, that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth Lord. It is neuertheleſſe ſo tranſlated, becauſe of the imperfection of our Engliſh tongue: for hauing no one word that ſignifieth a title of honour, and of doing good (which this word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie) <note place="margin">The word, <hi>benefactors,</hi> doth beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſignification of the word, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the godly interpreters (knowing <hi>voces</hi> to be <hi>rerum imagines)</hi> haue by this periphraſis <hi>gracious lords,</hi> ſought to ſet downe the meaning of our Sauiour Chriſt, vſing <hi>Lord</hi> for a title of honor, and <hi>gracious</hi> for a title of doing good.</p>
            <p>This title <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I reade to haue bene giuen to great perſonages, as to <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> the third of that name, after <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the immediat ſucceſſor of <hi>Ptolomeus Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphus,</hi> and to <hi>Ptolomeus,</hi> the ſeuenth after <hi>Alexander,</hi> and ſucceſſor of <hi>Ptolomeus Philometor,</hi> and as ſome write to <hi>Cleomenes</hi> king of <hi>Sparta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſence, being vſually giuen to great men, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt in this title doth not ſimply forbid the name of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but the ambitious affecting of that title, and ſo of honor, according as Matth. 23. 8. and 9. he forbiddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be called Rabbi, or father: where not the name ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but the ambicious affecting of that title is forbidden.</p>
            <p>Againe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a title of doing good, and all one with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which titles are indifferently giuen to all Chriſtians, magiſtrates, people, and Miniſters, in the Scriptures. And that it may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare, that this title is not forbidden, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> doth apply it to our ſauiour Chriſt. Actes. 10. 38. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vvhich vvent about doing good.</hi> And in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21700:7"/> this ſence our Sauiour Chriſt doth not forbid, ſimply, the name and title of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but the hauing or giuing of vaine titles, according as the Gentile rulers, which were called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: good-doers, being in deede bad-doers.</p>
            <p>In like maner, the title of Lord is not forbidden in this place, nor in any other place of Scripture, to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Our Sauiour Chriſt, in regard of his ſuperioritie ouer his Diſciples, was called Lord, Iohn 13. 13. <hi>You call me Lord, and Maister,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: yea the Apoſtles haue this name giuen them, Actes 16. 30. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>My Lords, vvhat shall I do that I may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> In which place neither Paul nor Silas do reprehend that title giuen them, which if it had bene vnlawfull, they would.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, the title of ruler, is in the Scripture giuen to Miniſters, Hebr. 13. 7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thoſe rulers vvhich haue preached vnto you the vvord of God.</hi> And in the ſeuenteenth verſe of the ſame chapter, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Obey thoſe rulers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As titles of honour are not forbidden to Miniſters: ſo not to other rulers. The old Teſtament is full of high ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles giuen vnto them: and ſo are there ſome in the New. The Euangeliſt Saint Luke, in his Goſpell, Chapter 1. 3. writing to Theophilus, giueth him this title: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>moſt excellent, or renovvned Theophilus:</hi> which title alſo Paule giueth to Feſtus, Actes 26. 25. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>moſt noble Feſtus.</hi> To be ſhort, if anie title of honor, were ſimply euil, it were the name and title of God giuen vnto men, but that title in the old Teſtament in diuerſe places, is giuen to rulers, and the ſame is confirmed to them by our Sauiour Chriſt, Iohn. 10. 34. Titles of honour are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21700:7"/> therefore neither forbidden to Ciuill, nor Eccleſiaſticall rulers.</p>
            <p>Nowe remaineth the ſecond ſence: <hi>The kings of the Gentiles, do rule: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not rule. This ſence can not agree with this place, for it is againſt all ſence, that where the titles of rulers are giuen, there ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhould be denied. And moſt certaine it is, that Chriſt in this place, forbiddeth vaine titles, and indeede there is nothing more vaine, than bare titles, without the thing itſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, our Sauiour Chriſt, in the words immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly following, doth graunt vnto them to beare rule, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereas, if his purpoſe had bene to forbid rule vnto them, he would haue ſayd, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rule therefore in this place is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
            <p>Now remaineth the third ſence, and that is this: <hi>The kings of the Gentiles do rule: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not ſo rule. And this is the true, and natural meaning of our Sauiour Chriſt: but this ſo ruling, that is, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ruling, is diuerſly taken of diuerſe men, and the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, attributed to diuerſe wordes, in the verſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before.</p>
            <p>Some attribute <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, making the ſence thus: <hi>The kings of the Gentiles, do rule: But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not rule as kings, and ſo vnderſtand by kings, ſupreme rulers, making our Sauiour Chriſt in this place to forbid ſupreme gouernment.</p>
            <p>Others attribute <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: &amp; do make the ſence thus, <hi>The kings of the Gentiles, do rule: But you, not ſo:</hi> that is, you ſhall not rule, vnderſtanding by rule, ciuill authoritie, and ſo make our Sauiour Chriſt in this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21700:8"/> place, to forbid Ciuill gouernment to his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Others attribute <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the ſame verbe, but by it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding tyrannous gouernment, &amp; ſo make the ſence to be this. <hi>The kings of the Gentiles do</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, rule tyrannouſly, or oppreſſe them: <hi>But you not ſo:</hi> that is, you my Diſciples ſhall not tyrannize.</p>
            <list>
               <item>So that in this place, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt doth forbid either
<list>
                     <item>Supreme,</item>
                     <item>Ciuill,</item>
                     <item>or Tyrannous gouernment.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Supreme gouernment is not forbidden: my reaſons are theſe. Firſt, becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place doth not ſignifie onely the ſupreme gouernour, for he ſpeaketh in the plurall number, and of many, there being at this time but one ſupreme gouernour, namely, <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi> And therfore by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are vnderſtood the inferior rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, according as in Scripture the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the inferiour ruler: as Marke 6. 14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Herod the king,</hi> whereas <hi>Herod</hi> was but an inferiour ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, vnder <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and ſo Matthew 2. 22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that Archelaus vvas king:</hi> whereas <hi>Archelaus</hi> was likewiſe an inferiour ruler. And this is likewiſe made plaine by the verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>do rule:</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the plurall number, of moe than one, and in the preſent tenſe, whereas onely <hi>Tiberius</hi> did at this time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſupreme gouernment.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is this, To exerciſe ſupreme authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is not ſimplie euill, as appeareth in that Paule doth appeale to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as ſupreme gouernour. Actes. 25. 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I appeale to Caeſar.</hi> As likewiſe, by the godly and Chriſtian gouernment, of <hi>Conſtantine, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> and others: allowed of, by ſo many, ſo learned, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21700:8"/> godly fathers. Therefore ſupreme gouernement is not in this place forbidden.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ciuill</hi> gouernment, is likewiſe not forbidden: my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are. Firſt, if it had bene the purpoſe of our Sauiour Chriſt, to forbid <hi>Ciuill</hi> gouernment: in all men: he wold haue ſayd, <hi>The kings of Iſraell haue ruled: But you not ſo.</hi> Or if his purpoſe had bene to forbid it in the Miniſterie, he would haue ſayd: <hi>The Prieſts of Iſraell do rule: But you not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, our Sauiour Chriſt in this place, and in this verſe, doth graunt to his Diſciples, that they may beare rule, when as he ſaith: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, our Sauiour Chriſt in this place, ſpeaketh to the whole Church, in which it is lawfull for ſome to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, both in the olde and new Teſtament the Prieſtes did exerciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie.</hi> And the Apoſtles do by their owne examples and writings, teſtifie the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 8 20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. 14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 16. 25 <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35. 1. 2. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. 3. 4.</note> herof. In the old Teſtament we reade that Noah, Melchiſedech, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, and Iob, did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice as Prieſts, and exerciſe authoritie as Rulers. But it may be, ſome will obiect againſt theſe, that they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, and before the Law.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we then ſay to Moſes, to whom manie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24 4. 5. 6. 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>Sic Bertramus in Politia Iud. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ad finem.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 1 3. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 7. 9. 15. 17 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 1.</note> learned men haue attributed both? But to come nearer, in the firſt booke of Samuell, we find Ely to be Iudge &amp; Prieſt: Samuell after him, Iudge and Prieſt: Ioell and Abia the ſonnes of Samuell, Iudges and Prieſts. All theſe ſucceeding one another. Succeſſion muſt of neceſſity take away extraordinarie. Yea, and of this gouernment God doth ſay, that it was his owne ordinance. 1. Samuel. 8. 7. <hi>They haue not caſt avvay thee, but me, that I should not</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21700:9"/> 
               <hi>raigne ouer them.</hi> The like may be ſaid of Eſdras, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 7. 14. 25 26. <hi>&amp; Nehem.</hi> 12 1. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5 14 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 2 1. 21</note> and Mattathias, commaunded, for to doe after the law of their God, &amp; zealous of the ſame law, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, would not haue exerciſed both, had not both bene lawfull to them, by the law of their God.</p>
            <p>Againe, what ſhall we ſay, to thoſe many examples, which diuerſe learned writers haue noted in Prieſtes. Some being deuiders of land: chiefe of Princes counſels: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſua</hi> 14. 1. 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 4. 2.</note> Captaines of armies: but eſpecially to that 1. Chron. 26. 30. 31. of Haſabias and Ieria, which by Dauid are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic Bertramus de Politia Iud. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>exponit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in miniſterio Dei, &amp; regis:</hi> both in Eccleſiaſticall, and Ciuill cauſes.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will obiect, that this was lawfull in the old Law, but not in the new. To which I anſwer, that if it were lawfull in the old, much more is it lawfull in the new. For if the Prieſtes, when the feaſtes were ſo manie, and their ſacrifices (as I may terme them) infinite, might intend to exerciſe Ciuill authoritie, vnder Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: much rather may the miniſters of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when as their feaſts and ſacrifices do ceaſe, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is farre more plainly, and plentifully preached.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome will farther obiect: What example haue you in the new Teſtament, of any Apoſtle, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Ciuill authoritie vnder Princes? To this I anſwer, that though there were no exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet doth not that proue, that it is vnlawfull: for then may we reaſon thus, There is no example in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of anie Chriſtian exerciſing the office of a king: therefore the office of a king is not lawfull: I thinke if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſhould ſo reaſon, he would be accounted a mad man. This therefore I ſay, that as we do reaſon from the olde Law, for the eſtabliſhing of the authoritie of the king,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21700:9"/> becauſe it was God his owne ordinance, and that ouer his owne people Iſraell, ſo from the ſame do we reaſon, that it is lawfull for Miniſters to exerciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Prieſtes by God his appointment, did exerciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie</hi> vnder Princes.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſtill obiect, Yea but what is the cauſe then? if it be ſo lawfull? that none, or verie fewe examples are found in the newe Teſtament, of Apoſtles, or other Miniſters, exerciſing <hi>Ciuill authoritie?</hi> To this I anſwer, that I take it, there were two eſpeciall reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe immediate delegation of authoritie, was an argument of exceeding fauour, as appeareth in <hi>Herod,</hi> his <hi>ſonnes,</hi> and the <hi>Agrippaes.</hi> The authoritie, was now eſpecially in the hands of heathen Princes, wicked men, and cruell tyrants, ſuch as hated Chriſt, the profeſſors of Chriſt, and much more the preachers of Chriſt, ſuch as the Apoſtles were. Now to exerciſe authoritie, without delegation, they would not, becauſe of Chriſt his words, Luke 12. 14. <hi>VVho hath made me a ruler?</hi> ſhewing, that becauſe he had not Ciuil authoritie delegated, he would not then exerciſe it.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon, which I alſo adde to this, is. Becauſe that the Apoſtles were ſent to preach throughout all the world, and therefore, hauing no certaine place, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in which alwayes to abide: how could they exerciſe authoritie by delegation from Princes: ſeeing they had no continuall abode in anie place.</p>
            <p>But leſt any ſhould thinke it vnlawfull for Miniſters to exerciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie,</hi> the Apoſtles, by their owne examples, (hauing this authoritie delegated with the conſent of the Church) haue left vs ſufficient light, to ſee the lawfulneſſe thereof.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21700:10"/>
            <p>Firſt of all therefore, we reade Act. 4. 35. that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was layed at the Apoſtles feet. If any denie that to be <hi>Ciuill,</hi> yet what is it to take account, both what they ſold, and for how much, which thing the Apoſtles did. But if any ſhall ſtill ſay, that this was not <hi>Ciuill,</hi> yet to deuide thoſe goods muſt neede be <hi>Ciuill,</hi> as appeareth by Chriſt his words, Luke 12. <hi>VVho hath made me a ruler, or a deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi> That the Apoſtles did deuide this mony, it appeareth in that it is ſaid, <hi>It vvas laid at the Apoſtles feet, &amp; deuided:</hi> why was it laid at their feete, but to be deuided? Againe, certaine it is, that they did deuide: for afterward, Actes 6. they choſe <hi>Deacons,</hi> to take from them the office of deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, becauſe the Church was now great, and they were to diſperſe them ſelues, to preach to all the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly we reade Act. 5. that <hi>Peter</hi> ſitteth, <hi>Iudicially</hi> vpon <hi>Saphira:</hi> for there <hi>Saphira</hi> appeareth before him, &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 7.</note> he reaſoneth with her, about the ſale of her goods, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Haue ye ſold it for thus much?</hi> He doth alſo proceede <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 58.</note> to ſentence of death, verſe 9. <hi>The feete of thoſe that buried thy husband, are at the doore, and shall carrie avvay thee.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 9.</note> If any ſhall obiect, that this was extraordinarie, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it was, in regard of the maner of her death, but not, the ſitting in iudgement vpon her, to examine her.</p>
            <p>Againe, we reade, 1. Timoth. 3. 4. that a Biſhop may be ruler of a houſe: in theſe wordes: <hi>ruling his ovvne houſe vvell:</hi> the which, may at the firſt, ſeeme a ſmall thing, to proue <hi>Ciuill authoritie</hi> to be lawfull in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, but being better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of, it importeth much. For, <hi>Ciuill authoritie</hi> is either <hi>Politicall,</hi> or <hi>Oeconomicall:</hi> and <hi>Oeconomicall</hi> is, of the Father, Maiſter, and Lord. If therefore a Biſhop as a Father, Maiſter, or Lord, exerciſe <hi>Ciuill authoritie,</hi> it cannot be, but that <hi>Ciuill authoritie</hi> is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21700:10"/> lawful. This againe is illuſtrated, in that the gouernment of a father, is the patterne of the gouernment of a king, &amp; therefore a king is called in the fift Commandement, a father, <hi>Honour father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle, in the ſame Epiſtle, 1. Tim. 5. 19. vſeth this exhortation to Timothie, the Biſhop of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Against an Elder, receiue no accuſation, vnder tvvo or three vvitneſſes.</hi> He graunteth to Timothie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue accuſations, or billes of complaint, and that he may proceed Iudicially, by two or three witneſſes, which is, by citing them, by examining them, &amp; by depoſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If any ſhall obiect, and ſay, that this is Eccleſiaſticall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Elder, <hi>a miniſter,</hi> I anſwer, that ſeeing <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> is put indefinitly, as in the Greeke: or elſe, as we reade it in Engliſh, <hi>no accuſation,</hi> generally, it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be <hi>Ciuil;</hi> for accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s alwayes, againſt Miniſters, are not Eccleſiaſtical, as appeareth, when as Miniſters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for fellonie, treaſon, or murther, are conuented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Ciuil</hi> magiſtrat, without any claime of his clergy.</p>
            <p>Againe, if it were Eccleſiaſticall, in regard of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, why ſhould it not be <hi>Ciuill</hi> in regard of the accuſers, the accuſers being lay men? for it is not ſayd, <hi>amongſt El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> that is, of one Elder againſt another: but <hi>againſt an Elder:</hi> that is, of lay men againſt Elders.</p>
            <p>Againe, if we read the words with an Emphaſis, as, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Elder receiue no accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they infer, that againſt thoſe that are no Elders, that is, lay men, he may proceed without three witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the ſame Apoſtle proceedeth, ver. 20. <hi>thoſe that ſinne, rebuke before all, that other may feare.</hi> verſe 21. <hi>I charge thee before God, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and his elect Angels, that thou obſerue theſe things,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21700:11"/> 
               <hi>vvithout preiudice:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth infer <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate, and a ſentence of iudgement, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inferreth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a iudge: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inferreth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to iudge: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he muſt: not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, iudge before hand, which is, before he hath cited the witneſſes, examined the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, depoſed the witneſſes, and had the number of two or three witneſſes. And therefore to expreſſe the meaning, he addeth: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which is, as <hi>Beza</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 21.</note> tranſlateth it, <hi>nihil faciens, in alteram partem declinando.</hi> The like phraſe of ſpeech being attributed Deut. 17. 20. to the <hi>Ciuill Magiſtrate.</hi> Therefore in this place <hi>Ciuill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> is not forbidden. There remaineth, tyrannous au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which is in this place forbidden: my reaſons are theſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Either Supreme, Ciuill, or Tyrannous gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is forbidden. But neither Supreme, nor Ciuill. Ergo Tyrannous.</hi> The force of this reaſon is manifeſted, in that which went before.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, not gouernment, but the maner of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is here forbidden, and that maner, was tyrannous; this I proue by theſe reaſons. Firſt, the kings that are here ſpoken of, did tyrannize, as for example, <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. 6. 13. 16. <hi>Marke</hi> 6. 18. 25. 26.</note> who condemned Chriſt an innocent: <hi>Herod Antipas,</hi> who tooke away his brother <hi>Philip</hi> his wife, and at the requeſt of a woman, put to death <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt: <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> of whoſe raigne <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is afrayd: <hi>Herodes magnus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. 22.</note> who ſlue many infants, and vnder the coulour of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8</note> Chriſt, ſought the ouerthrow of Chriſt and his kingdome. That theſe were the gouernours here ſpoken of, I proue, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, Marke 10. 42. <hi>you knovv,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe rulers, they knew, and theſe were they.</p>
            <p>Againe, Chriſt ſayth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and here <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: they do tyrannize: and ſpeaketh in the preſent tenſe: and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21700:11"/> ſome of theſe now ruled, and all theſe, in their gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tyrannized. And it plainly appeareth, that he onely ſpeaketh of tyrants, becauſe he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That this word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth ſignifie to tyrannize, I proue by the vſe of the ſame verbe, in other places of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, both old, and new Teſtament, as 1. Pet. 5. 3 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Act. 19. 16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And ſo Eſay 3. 4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Againe, the teſtimonie of learned writers, and godly fathers, expounding theſe places of the Euangeliſtes, do manifeſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eraſmus</hi> expoundeth it, <hi>Dominantur in eas, ſiue, aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Muſculus</hi> expoundeth it, <hi>potestate aduer ſum illos oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendos vtuntur.</hi> And a litle after, <hi>non regunt populum, ſed premunt, ſuiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> affectibus ſeruire cogunt, id quod eſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and expounding the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth it: <hi>potenter opprimunt inferiores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon theſe wordes, in Mathew, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it in like maner, and vpon the ſame wordes thus ſpeaketh, <hi>vt dominentur minoribus, vt ſeruificent, &amp; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lient, &amp; vſque ad mortem abutentur vita eorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſome wil obiect, that in this place the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple verbe is vſed, &amp; therfore not tyranny, but rule &amp; iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To this I anſwer, that the words which our Sauiour Chriſt here vſeth, do manifeſtly ſhew, and proue, that tyranny is forbidden, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this ſimple verbe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the wordes are, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which wordes can not be read, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>you shall not rule.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon, why in this ſimple verbe, tyrannie is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21700:12"/> forbidden, becauſe that this ſimple verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is vſed in the Scriptures, not for rule onely, but many times for a peruerſe kind of rule and for oppreſſion, as 2. Cor. 1. 24. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Rom. 6. 13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And in the old Teſtament, Dan. 11. 4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will obiect, that God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſayd <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I anſwer, that true it is: but God is ſaid <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe he ruleth after his owne will: his will being the perfect rule of iuſtice, whereas if man whoſe will is corrupt, ſhould rule after his owne will, it were meere tyrannie.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will further obiect, that true it is, that the ſimple verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is thus vſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but how proue you it to be ſo vſed in this place? To this I anſwer, that it is likewiſe vſed ſo in this place: and my reaſon is this, becauſe the verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is oppoſit to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this maner, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and againe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That this, is a fit and naturall oppoſition, appeareth by comparing this with the other Euangeliſts, for ſo Mat. 20. 26. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſubaudi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as here, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Againe, for the confirmation of this oppoſition, the conſent of all Harmonies, agreeing, that in al theſe Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, <hi>Mathevv, Marke,</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> one &amp; the ſame thing is handled and ſpoken, and therefore, all theſe muſt be compared together, and the ſimple verbe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place, is the ſame that the compound <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is in <hi>Mathevv</hi> and <hi>Marke.</hi> Adde vnto this the expoſition of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21700:12"/> all learned writers, which ſo farre as I haue read, do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret them, to be one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>As therefore in the wordes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: authoritie was commended, and not condemned in the Diſciples of our Sauiour Chriſt: ſo in this word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ambition, vaine titles, and tyrannie are onely forbidden, not ruling, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing authoritie, nor ſimply the deſire of bearing rule.</p>
            <p>There remaineth the laſt words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>you</hi> or <hi>amongeſt you.</hi> And theſe muſt in like maner be diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>In this place there is no doubt to be made, whether our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh to his Diſciples, <hi>Peter, Iames, Iohn, &amp;c.</hi> or not. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is therfore, whether our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh to his Diſciples, and none but them, or to his Diſciples, &amp; ſome repreſented by them. If we vnderſtand it to be ſpoken to them onely, then we take it to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken perſonally, that is, to his Diſciples and no other: ſo that then, nothing in this place, is either forbidden or commanded to others. But this is againſt ſence, and hath no reaſon whereupon it ſhould be grounded, and is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of no learned writer, and therefore I ſtand not to improue that.</p>
            <p>It is therefore ſpoken to the Diſciples, and ſome other repreſented by them, and thus it is taken <hi>Repreſentatiuely,</hi> that is, aſwell to thoſe that are repreſented by them, as to them.</p>
            <p>Hereof ariſeth this queſtion, whether our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh <hi>Repreſentatiuely</hi> to the whole Church, that is, all Chriſtians, Miniſters and people, or <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiuely</hi> to the Miniſters of the Church onely.</p>
            <p>In this place by <hi>you,</hi> our Sauiour doth vnderſtand the whole Church, that is, all Chriſtians, both Miniſters and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21700:13"/> people, and this I proue by theſe reaſons following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Diſciples to whom Chriſt ſpeaketh, had not as yet the office of preaching, and baptizing all nations, for this was after Chriſt his death committed to them: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 19.</note> whereas this was ſpoken in his life, and therefore repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chriſtians, not Miniſters onely. But admit they had that office, as theſe Diſciples are in this Chapter and other places of the Goſpell, called Apoſtles: and likewiſe had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 12. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 7.</note> the office of preaching, though I take it that were tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie, and to a certaine people; yet certaine it is, that theſe Diſciples in their perſons repreſent Chriſtians, as in their office Miniſters, and therfore, being ſpoken to them, why ſhould they not in this place, aſwell or rather, repreſent all: Miniſters and people, as Miniſters onely.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is. It were abſurd, to thinke that our Sauiour Chriſt doth forbid tyrannie to Miniſters onely, whereas tyrannie, being a thing ſimply euill, is more fitly forbidden to Miniſters and people, that is, all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>A third reaſon is: Our Sauiour Chriſt in this chapter, doth immediatly before, and alſo preſently after, vſing this word <hi>you,</hi> and ſpeaking to his Diſciples, &amp; none but them, as in this place, ſpeaketh to them, repreſenting the whole Church, and not the Miniſters onely: as in the 19. verſe of this 22. of Luke, in theſe wordes: <hi>This is my body, vvhich is giuen for you:</hi> by, <hi>you:</hi> in that place, (though it be ſpoken onely to the Diſciples, is not vnderſtood, the Miniſters onely, for then none might be ſaued but Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: but it is ſpoken to the whole Church, and the body of Chriſt is giuen to the Diſciples, that is, for all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Againe, verſe 20. <hi>This cup, is the nevv Teſtament, in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 20.</note> 
               <hi>my bloud, vvhich is povvred out for you.</hi> In which place, by, <hi>you:</hi> Chriſt meaneth, not only Miniſters, but all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21700:13"/> whom theſe Diſciples did now repreſent, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe none ſhould be ſaued but Miniſters, if the bloud of Chriſt were ſhed for none but them. And therfore <hi>S. Mat.</hi> chap. 26. ver. 28. expoundeth theſe words, ſaying, <hi>vvhich is shed for many.</hi> Againe in the words preſently after, ver. 29. <hi>I haue appointed vnto you, as my father hath appointed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 29</note> 
               <hi>vnto me, a kingdome:</hi> by, <hi>you:</hi> he vnderſtandeth, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: for vnto all true Chriſtians, he hath appointed a kingdome.</p>
            <p>But it hath bene obiected, that our Sauiour Chriſt, in this Chapter, ſpeaketh to his Diſciples, vſing the word <hi>you,</hi> and yet ſpeaketh not to them, repreſenting the whole Church. To which I now anſwer, that true it is, that our Sauiour Chriſt in this Chapter, ſaith, <hi>I haue earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to eate vvith you. &amp;c. I ſay vnto you. &amp;c.</hi> But I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that in theſe places he ſpeaketh <hi>Perſonally:</hi> that is, to his Diſciples onely, and no other repreſented by them. Now the queſtion is not, whether it be taken <hi>Perſonally,</hi> or <hi>Repreſentatiuely;</hi> for then this were (though litle to the purpoſe) yet <hi>ad idem:</hi> but in this place, the queſtion is, whether he ſpeak <hi>repreſentatiuely,</hi> to the Miniſters of the Church onely, or <hi>repreſentatiuely</hi> to the whole Church. If therefore there can be brought out of this Chapter, ſo many places, ſo manifeſt as theſe are, in which Chriſt ſpeaketh to his Diſciples, and none but them, as he doth in this place, and yet as repreſenting the Miniſters onely, &amp; not other Chriſtians, then ſhall that beare ſome ſtroke, &amp; come to be ballanced with the weight of theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>A fourth reaſon is this. The oppoſition in this place, which is betweene <hi>Gentiles</hi> &amp; <hi>you,</hi> doth manifeſtly proue that it is ſpoken to the whole Church. As for example, <hi>The kings of the Gentiles, do tyrannize ouer them:</hi> that is,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21700:14"/> the people. Amongſt theſe are kings tyrannizing, &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nized. <hi>But you not ſo,</hi> or, <hi>it shall not be ſo vvith you.</hi> that is, I do command, that with you there ſhould be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kings tyrannizing, nor people tyrannized. It is thus with them: <hi>it shall not be ſo vvith you Miniſters:</hi> is neither right, nor good oppoſition. It is thus with the Gentiles, <hi>it shall not be thus vvith you Chriſtians,</hi> is a fit, good, and ſenſible oppoſition. So then, the oppoſition betweene the kings of the Gentiles tyrannizing, and people tyrannized, and <hi>you,</hi> doth proue manifeſtly, that Chriſt meaneth not onely Miniſters, but alſo people, that is, all Chriſtians, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom he would haue neither tyrants, nor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tyrannized.</p>
            <p>Againe this is manifeſt to be Chriſt his meaning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in like maner, in the ſcriptures ſpeaking of Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and making an oppoſition betwixt them &amp; others, the oppoſition is between Gentils and Chriſtians, &amp; not betweene Gentiles and Miniſters: as Mat. 6. ver. 7. 8. <hi>The Gentiles do thinke, that by their much babling they shall be heard. Be not you like vnto them:</hi> that is, be not you my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, you that take my name in your mouths, that heare me, that profeſſe your ſelues to be Chriſtians. And againe in the ſame Chapter, verſe 32. <hi>After all theſe things do the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>Gentiles ſeeke,</hi> and therefore ſaith to them, verſe 31. <hi>Be not you therefore carefull, &amp;c. for your heauenly Father knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, &amp;c.</hi> In which place, our Sauiour doth plainly make an oppoſition, betwixt thoſe he ſpake to, that is, his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and thoſe that heard him, and Gentiles, that is, thoſe that were ſpoken of, to whom he would not haue his Diſciples, that is, Chriſtians to be like.</p>
            <p>A fift reaſon is, this place compared with that of Mat. chap. 23. verſ. 8. 9. doth ſhew plainely, that it is ſpoken to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21700:14"/> the whole Church: for in that chapter our Sauior Chriſt ſpeaketh of the ſame matter, vſeth a like forme of words, and the very ſame words: as for example, <hi>The Scribes and the Phariſies are called Rabbi, &amp;c. But be not you ſo called</hi> &amp; in this Chapter is the like. <hi>They that are in authoritie are called</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>But you not ſo.</hi> Againe ver. 11. <hi>But let him that is the greater, be as the miniſter.</hi> Which words are in the former places of the Euangeliſts. Now, if one place of Scripture is to be expounded by another, and the darker by that which is more plain, theſe in like maner, may one be expounded by another. If any ſhall aske, how I proue that our Sauiour Chriſt, in this 23. of Mathew, ſpeaketh to the whole Church, I anſwer, that it manifeſtly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, in that in the firſt verſe of that Chapter, it is ſayed, <hi>Then ſpake Ieſus, to the multitude, and his Diſciples.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This might further be ſtrengthened and confirmed, by the opinion of ancient, and late writers (ſome whereof I haue before mentioned.) But theſe reaſons are apparant and very ſufficient: I therfore conclude, that our Sauiour ſpeaketh in this place to all men: forbidding all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ambitiouſly to ſtriue for honor, or to tyrannize ouer the people. What our Sauiour commandeth, is contained in the words following, <hi>But let him that shalbe greater, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord of his infinit mercie, graunt, that all Rulers may learne, to follovv the commandement of Chriſt, neither am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly ſtriuing for higher places, nor by vniuſtice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie abuſing the lovver: then shal God be glorified, and vve his people liue a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſtie. VVhich he graunt, vvho hath bought vs vvith his precious bloud, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous. To vvhom, vvith the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, be all honor and glorie vvorld vvithout end.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
